Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, it’s part two of our
series on fluoride in water.
And we’ll start with some new research
that helped me change my own mind
about the safety of fluoridation.
Community water fluoridation
recently hit
its 75th anniversary,
touted as a significant
advancement in public health,
but new research
suggests the potential
for adverse health impacts.
There's little question
that supplemental fluoride
strengthens teeth
and reduces decay.
But at what cost?
Most of the older studies
were snapshot-in-time studies,
looking only at group-level data
or were based on
higher-than-normal exposure.
That has since changed
with the publication
of prospective studies
following individual
exposure levels from
mother-child pairs over time.
The first few were from Mexico
and correlated
higher fluoride levels
in the urine of pregnant women
with future developmental delay
in their infants.
They found worse cognitive
performance at age four
and lower IQ
from ages six through 12,
but the fluoride was
from fluoridated salt
or water sources where fluoride
was present naturally.
Then, this study
came out of Canada,
the first prospective study
using individual exposure data
dealing directly with
community water fluoridation
receiving quote-unquote
"optimally fluoridated" water.
None of the municipal
water fluoride levels
exceeded 1.5 parts per million,
and the vast majority,
over 90 percent,
were under the U.S.
target of point seven.
Despite drinking
"optimally fluoridated water,"
the study of more than
500 mother-child pairs
found that higher fluoride
exposure during pregnancy,
once again,
appeared to translate
into lower child intelligence,
measured at ages three to four.
The American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists
recommends pregnant women drink
at least eight cups
of water a day.
Based on the Canadian study,
following this advice
with water at U.S.
target fluoridation levels
might result in as much as
a 5-point loss in IQ.
The Canadian study was published
in the American
Medical Association's
pediatrics journal,
the longest running pediatrics
journal in the country.
The editor-in-chief defended its
decision to publish the study
"as testament to the fact that
JAMA Pediatrics is committed
to disseminating
the best science...
regardless of how contentious
the results may be."
The Canadian Agency
for Drugs and Technologies
in Health
issued a rapid response report,
concluding that there
is insufficient evidence
to conclusively conclude
that fluoride exposure
at optimum levels affects
neurological development,
but that's not what
the Canadian study was saying.
The researchers just suggested
the "possible need"
to reduce fluoride intake
during pregnancy.
As the accompanying
editorial concluded,
based on the new data,
"a dispassionate
and tempered discussion
of fluoride's potential
neurotoxicity is warranted."
What was the response
from US regulators?
Within a month of
the Canadian study's release,
the National Toxicology Program,
which is part
of the US Department
of Health and Human Services
that evaluates substances
for potentially harmful
human health effects,
released a draft evaluation
of fluoride exposure
and neurodevelopmental
and cognitive health effects
and concluded that,
"Based on a systematic review
of the evidence,
the NTP concludes that
fluoride is presumed to be
a cognitive neurodevelopmental
hazard to humans."
So we've gone
from dismissing people
who questioned the safety
of water fluoridation
as zealots
or anti-science fanatics,
to the official US National
Toxicology Program saying
we should presume
it's hazardous.
Now, this was just
a draft report.
To ensure the integrity
of its report,
the NTP asked
the National Academies,
probably our most prestigious
scientific institution,
to review it.
The review raised
a bunch of concerns,
which was portrayed
in the dental literature
as "discrediting"
the IQ research.
But that's not what
the National Academies said.
They explicitly said that
their misgivings don't mean
that the NTP conclusion
that fluoride should be presumed
to be neurotoxic is incorrect;
they just wanted
some further analysis.
So, in 2020,
they redrafted their draft,
and once again came
to the same conclusion,
presuming it's a cognitive
neurodevelopmental hazard
based on the extent,
consistency,
and robustness of the IQ data.
The National Academies
then rereviewed
their redrafted draft,
concluding it's much improved,
but urged the NTP
to further improve
the clarity of the document,
and we await
the final NTP report.
In our final story,
we look at medicine’s response to the
changing science on fluoride safety.
The National Toxicology Program
is part of the
Public Health Service,
in partnership with
the CDC, FDA, and NIH,
dedicated to the analysis
of agents of concern
to identify any toxic effects.
How did the medical community
respond to the draft conclusions
in their recent systematic
review that concluded that
fluoride is to be presumed to be
a cognitive neurodevelopmental
hazard to humans,
based on studies
showing lower IQ scores
among kids with
higher fluoride exposure?
What do you do
when current research
contradicts public practices,
when new evidence doesn't
conform with existing beliefs?
Well, health authorities
have continued to conclude
that fluoride is
unequivocally safe,
despite the new studies
in recent years
linking fluoride
exposure in pregnancy
with adverse effects
on fetal brain development.
There are still papers
on how to "sell"
fluoridation
of the water supply,
targeting social media
and the person-to-person spread
of fluoride "misinformation."
Search engines are to be
encouraged, at the very least,
to flag search engine results
that point to water fluoridation
health "misinformation"
suggesting adverse effects.
In promoting support for
community water fluoridation,
maybe we don't even want
to proclaim its safety
for fear of raising
questions about risks.
I mean, if you're
saying it's safe,
then that begs the question,
"Well, is it not safe?"
Maybe we shouldn't even
talk about whether it's safe.
The tendency
to ignore new evidence
that does not conform
to widespread beliefs
may be impeding
our response to early warnings
about fluoride as a potential
developmental neurotoxin,
but some are just so
fixed in their views
on fluoridation that they
won't reassess their stance
no matter what
the latest research might show.
Ironically, it was
the antifluoridationists
who were accused of their
"anti-scientific attitudes,"
but now it's the
pro-fluoridationists.
One of the most facile
pro-fluoridation arguments
I ran across is the suggestion
that fluoride
can't be hurting IQs,
because over the last
half century of fluoridation,
IQ scores have been going up
rather than down.
The jaw-dropping irony is that
a substantial part
of that rise may have been due
to the removal of another
neurotoxic element, lead.
It's worth remembering
that the science surrounding
the neurodevelopmental hazard
of low-level lead exposure
was also bitterly contested
using the same kinds
of arguments we see today
in the fluoridation debate.
A few short years
before leaded gas
was effectively banned
in the United States,
a meta-analysis of
lead exposure and child IQ
only found 24 human studies,
all cross-sectional,
with a typical associated
loss in intelligence
of about four IQ points.
The current data suggest
a similar IQ loss from fluoride
from an even stronger
body of evidence.
A spokesperson for
the American Dental Association
responded to the new data
by pointing out
that some cities that
have ended water fluoridation
saw an increase in cavities.
Okay, but that's kind
of a strange response
to data suggesting the potential
for permanent brain damage
in children.
I mean, I know they are
the dental association,
but how could they so easily
ignore the serious red flags
of potential neurotoxicity
for cavity reduction?
This is not to say tooth decay
isn't a serious health issue,
but there are ways to get the
cavity-preventing benefits
of fluoride without the risks.
Since the primary benefits arise
from topical contact
with our enamel,
but the primary risks arise
from systemic absorption,
we can follow Europe's example
and safely reap the rewards
using fluoride toothpaste
and mouthwashes.
In Europe, 98 percent
of the population
drink unfluoridated water.
Several countries,
including France, Germany,
the Netherlands, Denmark,
Sweden, banned fluoridation
decades ago in favor
of fluoride toothpaste,
as more than ten years ago,
the official scientific
committee on health risks
of the European Union concluded
that topical application
of fluoride is most effective
in preventing tooth decay
and that there appears to be
no obvious advantage
in favor of fluoridating
the water supply.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.